Rhiannon: We all need to become
better at understanding, how we
can help children and young people
to thrive and be mentally healthy.
By having resilience, children and
young people can gain the strength
to cope when something goes wrong and
have the ability to solve problems,
so they can remain mentally healthy,
or bounce back from times of stress.
Leah: Family and social relationships,
self-esteem and personal values, aid
resilience and there are skills that
can be learnt to cope better with
stress and improve resilience further.
Resilience in children and young
people can be boosted by support from
family, friends, neighbours and even
pets, as positive interactions with
those who are close can help relieve
stress and shape good memories.
Rhiannon: Recalling good memories also
improves resilience in vulnerable young
people which helps them to better cope
with the stresses they’re experiencing,
such as remembering the fun times they
have had with their friends and family.
Leah: Building resilience in young people
may help to protect against engaging in
health risk behaviour, such as smoking,
drinking alcohol, illicit drug use and
unprotected sex and can also help to delay
‘transitions’ such as parenthood, which
can in turn help to avoid the potential
negative health consequences of early
pregnancy for both parents and babies.
Rhiannon: Resilience can contribute to
healthy behaviours, higher qualifications
and skills, better employment, better
mental wellbeing, and quicker or more
successful recovery from illness.